So many of you have probably seen the movie "The Martian."
ربما شاهد الكثير منكم فيلم (المريخي).
But for those of you who did not, it's a movie about an astronaut
أما الذين لم يشاهدوه، فهو فيلم حول رائد فضاء
who is stranded on Mars, and his efforts to stay alive
بقي عالقاً على سطح المريخ، وجهوده للبقاء على قيد الحياة
until the Earth can send a rescue mission to bring him back to Earth.
إلى أن يتم إرسال فريق إنقاذ لإعادته إلى الأرض.
Gladly, they do re-establish communication
لحسن الحظ، استطاعوا إعادة ربط الاتصال
with the character, astronaut Watney, at some point
مع الشخصية، رائد الفضاء (واتني) في لحظة ما
so that he's not as alone on Mars until he can be rescued.
حتى لا يكون وحيداً على المريخ إلى أن يتم إنقاذه.
So while you're watching the movie, or even if you haven't,
فخلال مشاهدتك للفيلم، أو حتى إذا لم تشاهده
when you think about Mars,
عند التفكير حول المريخ،
you're probably thinking about how far away it is and how distant.
من المحتمل أنك ستفكّر في بعد المسافة وكم هو بعيد.
And, what might not have occurred to you is,
وما قد لا يطرأ على بالك هو،
what are the logistics really like of working on another planet --
كيف هي الأمور اللوجستية للعمل على كوكب آخر --
of living on two planets
للعيش على كوكبين
when there are people on the Earth and there are rovers or people on Mars?
عندما يكون هناك أناس على الأرض ومراكب متجوّلة أو أناس على المريخ؟
So think about when you have friends, families and co-workers
فكر في أصدقائك وأهلك وزملاء عملك
in California, on the West Coast or in other parts of the world.
في كاليفورنيا، على الساحل الغربي أو في مناطق أخرى من العالم.
When you're trying to communicate with them,
عندما تحاول التواصل معهم،
one of the things you probably first think about is:
من أول الأشياء التي ربما ستفكّر فيها هي:
wait, what time is it in California?
مهلًا، كم هي الساعة في كاليفورنيا؟
Will I wake them up? Is it OK to call?
هل سأوقظهم؟ هل لا بأس بالاتصال؟
So even if you're interacting with colleagues who are in Europe,
حتى عندما تتواصل مع زملاء في أوروبا،
you're immediately thinking about:
تفكّر تلقائياً في:
What does it take to coordinate communication when people are far away?
ماذا يستلزم لتنسيق التواصل مع أشخاص بعيدين؟
So we don't have people on Mars right now, but we do have rovers.
ليس لدينا أناس على المريخ الآن، ولكن لدينا مركبات متجوّلة.
And actually right now, on Curiosity, it is 6:10 in the morning.
وفي هذه اللحظة، على (كريوستي)، إنها 6:10 صباحاً.
So, 6:10 in the morning on Mars.
إذاً، الساعة 6:10 صباحاً على المريخ.
We have four rovers on Mars.
لدينا أربع مركبات متجوّلة على المريخ.
The United States has put four rovers on Mars since the mid-1990s,
وضعت الولايات المتحدة أربع مركبات متجوّلة على المريخ منذ منتصف التسعينات،
and I have been privileged enough to work on three of them.
وكان لي شرف العمل على ثلاث منهم.
So, I am a spacecraft engineer, a spacecraft operations engineer,
فأنا مهندسة مركبات فضائية، مهندسة عمليّات مركبات فضائيّة،
at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Los Angeles, California.
في معمل ناسا لدفع الطائرات النفّاثة في لوس أنجلس، كاليفورنيا.
And these rovers are our robotic emissaries.
وهذه المركبات المتجوّلة هي مبعوثاتنا الآلية.
So, they are our eyes and our ears, and they see the planet for us
فهي أعيننا وآذاننا، وترينا الكوكب
until we can send people.
إلى أن نستطيع إرسال أناس إليه.
So we learn how to operate on other planets through these rovers.
فنحن نتعلم كيف نعمل على كواكب أخرى عن طريق هذه المركبات المتجوّلة.
So before we send people, we send robots.
فقبل أن نرسل أناساً، نرسل رجالاً آليين.
So the reason there's a time difference on Mars right now,
السبب وراء وجود فرق في التوقيت على المريخ الآن،
from the time that we're at
عن الوقت الذي نحن فيه
is because the Martian day is longer than the Earth day.
هو أن اليوم المريخي أطول من يوم الأرض.
Our Earth day is 24 hours,
يومنا على الأرض هو 24 ساعة،
because that's how long it takes the Earth to rotate,
لأنّ هذا هو الوقت الذي تحتاجه الأرض لتلف،
how long it takes to go around once.
الوقت المستغرق لتدور مرة واحدة.
So our day is 24 hours.
لذلك فإن يومنا هو 24 ساعة.
It takes Mars 24 hours and approximately 40 minutes to rotate once.
يستلزم المريخ 24 ساغة وتقريبًا 40 دقيقة ليدور مرةً واحدة.
So that means that the Martian day is 40 minutes longer than the Earth day.
هذا يعني أن اليوم المريخي أطول من يوم الأرض بـ 40 دقيقة.
So teams of people who are operating the rovers on Mars, like this one,
لذلك فإن فِرَقُ الأشخاص الذين يشغّلون المركبات المتجوّلة على المريخ، مثل هذا،
what we are doing is we are living on Earth, but working on Mars.
ما نفعله هو أنّنا نعيش في الأرض، ولكنّنا نعمل في المريخ.
So we have to think as if we are actually on Mars with the rover.
لذلك علينا أن نفكّر وكأننا فعليّاً على المريخ مع المركبة المتجوّلة.
Our job, the job of this team, of which I'm a part of,
عملنا، عمل هذا الفريق، الذي أنا جزء منه،
is to send commands to the rover to tell it what to do the next day.
هو إرسال أوامر للمركبة المتجوّلة لإخبارها ماذا تفعل في اليوم التالي.
To tell it to drive or drill or tell her whatever she's supposed to do.
لنخبرها أن تدفع أو تثقب أو نخبرها أيّاً كان ما عليها فعله.
So while she's sleeping -- and the rover does sleep at night
فحينما تكون نائمة -- والمركبة المتجوّلة فعلاً تنام مساءً
because she needs to recharge her batteries
لأنها تحتاج لإعادة شحن بطارياتها
and she needs to weather the cold Martian night.
وتحتاج إلى التعايش مع الليلة المريخية الباردة.
And so she sleeps.
لذلك فهي تخلد للنوم.
So while she sleeps, we work on her program for the next day.
فبينما تكون نائمة، نعمل نحن على إعداد برنامجها لليوم التالي.
So I work the Martian night shift.
أنا أعمل مناوبة الليل المريخي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So in order to come to work on the Earth at the same time every day on Mars --
إذاً لكي تأتي للعمل على الأرض في نفس الوقت يوميّاً في المريخ --
like, let's say I need to be at work at 5:00 p.m.,
كمثال، الساعة 5:00 مساءً،
this team needs to be at work at 5:00 p.m. Mars time every day,
على هذا الفريق أن يباشر العمل عند الساعة 5:00 مساءً بتوقيت المريخ كل يوم،
then we have to come to work on the Earth 40 minutes later every day,
فإذاً علينا أن نأتي للعمل على الأرض متأخّرين 40 دقيقةً كل يوم،
in order to stay in sync with Mars.
حتى نبقى بتزامن مع المريخ.
That's like moving a time zone every day.
كأن تنتقل لمنطقة زمنية مختلفة كل يوم.
So one day you come in at 8:00, the next day 40 minutes later at 8:40,
فتأتي يوماً ما الساعة 8:00، اليوم التالي تتأخر 40 دقيقة للساعة 8:40،
the next day 40 minutes later at 9:20,
واليوم التالي تتأخر 40 دقيقة للساعة 9:20،
the next day at 10:00.
واليوم التالي الساعة 10:00.
So you keep moving 40 minutes every day,
فتبقى تتقدم 40 دقيقة كل يوم،
until soon you're coming to work in the middle of the night --
حتى تأتي للعمل قريباً في منتصف الليل --
the middle of the Earth night.
في منتصف ليل الأرض.
Right? So you can imagine how confusing that is.
صحيح؟ فلك أن تتخيل كم هذا مربك.
Hence, the Mars watch.
بالتالي، ساعة المريخ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This weights in this watch have been mechanically adjusted
هذه الأوزان بهذه الساعة تم تعديلها ميكانيكيًّا
so that it runs more slowly.
فهي تعمل بسرعة أبطأ.
Right? And we didn't start out --
صحيح؟ ولم نبدأ --
I got this watch in 2004
حصلت على هذه الساعة في العام 2004
when Spirit and Opportunity, the rovers back then.
وقت عودة المركبات المتجولّة (سبيريت) و(أوبرتيونيتي).
We didn't start out thinking
لم نفكّر حينها
that we were going to need Mars watches.
أننا سنحتاج لساعات المريخ.
Right? We thought, OK, we'll just have the time on our computers
صحيح؟ فكّرنا، حسناً، فقط سنضبط الوقت على حواسيبنا
and on the mission control screens, and that would be enough.
وعلى شاشات التحكّم بالمهمات، وسيكون هذا كافياً.
Yeah, not so much.
نعم، ليس الكثير.
Because we weren't just working on Mars time,
لأنّنا لم نكن نعمل فحسب على توقيت المريخ،
we were actually living on Mars time.
بل كنّا في الواقع نعيش على توقيت المريخ.
And we got just instantaneously confused about what time it was.
وأصبحنا لحظيّاً مربكين بخصوص الوقت حينها.
So you really needed something on your wrist to tell you:
ففعليّاً تحتاج لشيء على ساعدك ليخبرك:
What time is it on the Earth? What time is it on Mars?
كم هي الساعة على الأرض؟ كم هي الساعة على المريخ؟
And it wasn't just the time on Mars that was confusing;
ولم يكن الوقت في المريخ فقط هو المربك:
we also needed to be able to talk to each other about it.
احتجنا لأن نكون قادرين أيضاً على أن نحدّث بعضنا عنه.
So a "sol" is a Martian day -- again, 24 hours and 40 minutes.
إذاً (سول) هو يوم مريخي -- مجدداً، 24 ساعة و40 دقيقة.
So when we're talking about something that's happening on the Earth,
فعندما نتحدث عن شيء يحدث في الأرض،
we will say, today.
نقول، اليوم،
So, for Mars, we say, "tosol."
في المريخ، نقول "السول".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yesterday became "yestersol" for Mars.
الأمس أصبح "الأمسول" في المريخ.
Again, we didn't start out thinking, "Oh, let's invent a language."
مجددًا، لم نفكر هكذا: "هيا لنخترع لغة".
It was just very confusing.
لقد كان مربكاً جدّاً.
I remember somebody walked up to me and said,
أذكر شخصاً دنى منّي وقال،
"I would like to do this activity on the vehicle tomorrow, on the rover."
"أرغب بعمل هذا النشاط على المركبة غداً، على المركبة المتجوّلة".
And I said, "Tomorrow, tomorrow, or Mars, tomorrow?"
فقلت: "غداً غداً، أم غداً المريخ؟"
We started this terminology because we needed a way to talk to each other.
استحدثنا هذه المصطلحات لأنّنا احتجنا لطريقة نحدث بها بعضنا البعض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Tomorrow became "nextersol" or "solorrow."
أصبح الغد "سولتالي" أو "سولغداً".
Because people have different preferences for the words they use.
لأن الناس لهم تفضيلات مختلفة للكلمات التي يستعملونها.
Some of you might say "soda" and some of you might say "pop."
بعضكم قد يقول "صودا" وبعضكم قد يقول "بوب".
So we have people who say "nextersol" or "solorrow."
فلدينا أناس يقولون "سولتالي" أو "سولغداً".
And then something that I noticed after a few years of working on these missions,
ولاحظت بعد عدة سنين من العمل على هذه المهمات،
was that the people who work on the rovers, we say "tosol."
أن الأشخاص العاملين على المركبات المتجولة، نقول "السول".
The people who work on the landed missions that don't rove around,
الأشخاص العاملين على المهمات التي هبطت ولا تتجول،
they say "tosoul."
يقولون "السوول".
So I could actually tell what mission you worked on from your Martian accent.
فأستطيع أن أعرف على أي مهمّة عملت من لكنتك المريخية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we have the watches and the language, and you're detecting a theme here, right?
فلدينا الساعات واللغة، فأنتم تجدون قالباً هنا، صحيح؟
So that we don't get confused.
حتى لا نصاب بالإرتباك.
But even the Earth daylight could confuse us.
لكن حتى ضوء النهار في الأرض يمكن أن يربكنا.
If you think that right now, you've come to work
فإذا أتيت إلى العمل الآن،
and it's the middle of the Martian night
في منتصف الليل المريخي
and there's light streaming in from the windows
وهناك ضوء من النوافذ
that's going to be confusing as well.
سيكون ذلك مربكاً.
So you can see from this image of the control room
فتستطيع أن ترى من هذه الصورة لغرفة التحكم
that all of the blinds are down.
أن كل العواتم منزلة.
So that there's no light to distract us.
فلا يكون هناك ضوء ليشتّت انتباهنا.
The blinds went down all over the building about a week before landing,
أنزلت العواتم على كل المبنى بأسبوع قبل الهبوط،
and they didn't go up until we went off Mars time.
ولم ترفع مجدداً حتى خرجنا من توقيت المريخ.
So this also works for the house, for at home.
هذا أيضاً يطبّق في المنزل.
I've been on Mars time three times, and my husband is like,
كنت على توقيت المريخ لثلاث مرات، ودائمًا يقول زوجي،
OK, we're getting ready for Mars time.
حسناً، نحن نستعدّ لتوقيت المريخ.
And so he'll put foil all over the windows and dark curtains and shades
فيضع القصدير على كل النوافذ وستائر غامقة وتظليل
because it also affects your families.
لأنه أيضاً يؤثّر على عائلاتكم.
And so here I was living in kind of this darkened environment, but so was he.
فعندما كنت أعيش في بيئة مظلمة، كان هو أيضاً كذلك.
And he'd gotten used to it.
وقد اعتاد على الأمر.
But then I would get these plaintive emails from him when he was at work.
لكن عندها تأتيني هذه الرسائل الحزينة منه عندما يكون في العمل.
Should I come home? Are you awake?
هل آتي إلى المنزل؟ هل أنتِ مستيقظة؟
What time is it on Mars?
كم هي الساعة على المريخ؟
And I decided, OK, so he needs a Mars watch.
فقررت، حسناً، هو يحتاج لساعة المريخ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But of course, it's 2016, so there's an app for that.
لكن بالطبع، إنها 2016، يوجد تطبيق لذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So now instead of the watches, we can also use our phones.
فالآن عوضاً عن الساعات، نستطيع أيضاً استعمال هواتفنا.
But the impact on families was just across the board;
لكن التأثير على العوائل كان يشمل الجميع.
it wasn't just those of us who were working on the rovers
لم يكن نحن فقط من يعمل على المركبات المتجولة
but our families as well.
ولكن عوائلنا أيضاً.
This is David Oh, one of our flight directors,
هذا (ديفيد أوه)، أحد مديري رحلاتنا،
and he's at the beach in Los Angeles with his family at 1:00 in the morning.
على الشاطئ في لوس أنجلس مع عائلته الساعة 1:00 بعد منتصف الليل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So because we landed in August
فلأنّنا هبطنا في شهر أغسطس
and his kids didn't have to go back to school until September,
ولم يتوجّب على أبناءه العودة للمدرسة حتى سبتمبر،
they actually went on to Mars time with him for one month.
قضوا معه الوقت بتوقيت المريخ لمدة شهر.
They got up 40 minutes later every day.
استيقظوا 40 دقيقة متأخرة كل يوم.
And they were on dad's work schedule.
وكانوا على جدول عمل أبيهم.
So they lived on Mars time for a month and had these great adventures,
فعاشوا على توقيت المريخ لشهر وحظوا بهذه المغامرات الممتعة،
like going bowling in the middle of the night
مثل لعب البولينج في منتصف الليل
or going to the beach.
أو الذهاب للشاطئ.
And one of the things that we all discovered
وأحد الأشياء التي اكتشفناها جميعاً
is you can get anywhere in Los Angeles
هو أنك تستطيع الذهاب لأي مكان في لوس أنجلس
at 3:00 in the morning when there's no traffic.
الساعة 3:00 صباحاً عندما لا تكون هناك زحمة سير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we would get off work,
فنخرج من العمل،
and we didn't want to go home and bother our families,
ولم نرد الذهاب لمنازلنا وإزعاج عوائلنا،
and we were hungry, so instead of going locally to eat something,
وكنّا جائعين، فبدل الذهاب لنأكل شيئاً في المنطقة،
we'd go, "Wait, there's this great all-night deli in Long Beach,
كنا نقول: "مهلاً، يوجد ذلك المطعم الليلي على (لونق بيتش)،
and we can get there in 10 minutes!"
ونستطيع أن نصل إليه في 10 دقائق!"
So we would drive down -- it was like the 60s, no traffic.
فنقود إليه -- مثل الستينيات، لا زحمة سير.
We would drive down there, and the restaurant owners would go,
نذهب إليه، وأصحاب المطعم يقولون:
"Who are you people?
"من أنتم أيها الناس؟
And why are you at my restaurant at 3:00 in the morning?"
ولماذا أنتم في مطعمي في الساعة 3:00 صباحاً؟"
So they came to realize that there were these packs of Martians,
فاستوعبوا أن هناك قطائع من المرّيخيين،
roaming the LA freeways, in the middle of the night --
يتجوّلون في طرق لوس أنجلس السريعة، في منتصف الليل --
in the middle of the Earth night.
في منتصف ليل الأرض.
And we did actually start calling ourselves Martians.
وقمنا فعليّاً بتسمية أنفسنا مرّيخيين.
So those of us who were on Mars time would refer to ourselves as Martians,
فالذين يعيشون منّا على توقيت المريخ نسمّي أنفسنا مريخيين،
and everyone else as Earthlings.
ونسمي كل آحد آخر أرضي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's because when you're moving a time-zone every day,
وهذا لأنك عندما تنتقل إلى منطقة زمنية جديدة يوميّاً،
you start to really feel separated from everyone else.
تشعر بأنك حقّاً منفصل عن أي أحد آخر.
You're literally in your own world.
أنت حرفيّاً في عالمك الخاص.
So I have this button on that says, "I survived Mars time. Sol 0-90."
فلدي هذا الوسام ومكتوب عليه، "أنا نجوت من توقيت المريخ. سول 0-90".
And there's a picture of it up on the screen.
وهنا صورة له على الشاشة.
So the reason we got these buttons is because we work on Mars time
فسبب حصولنا على هذه الأوسمة هو أننا نعمل على توقيت المريخ
in order to be as efficient as possible with the rover on Mars,
حتى نكون بأعلى كفاءة مع المركبة المتجوّلة في المريخ،
to make the best use of our time.
حتى نستعمل وقتنا بأفضل طريقة ممكنة.
But we don't stay on Mars time for more than three to four months.
لكنّنا لا نبقى على توقيت المريخ لأكثر من ثلاثة إلى أربعة شهور.
Eventually, we'll move to a modified Mars time, which is what we're working now.
تدريجيّاً، سننتقل إلى توقيت معدّل للمريخ، وهو ما نعمله الآن.
And that's because it's hard on your bodies, it's hard on your families.
وهذا لأنه صعب على أجسادكم، صعب على عائلاتكم.
In fact, there were sleep researchers who actually were studying us
في الحقيقة، كان هناك باحثون في النوم قاموا فعليّاً بدراستنا
because it was so unusual for humans to try to extend their day.
لأنه كان غير طبيعي للغاية للإنسان أن يحاول إطالة يومه.
And they had about 30 of us
وأخذوا ما يقارب 30 منّا
that they would do sleep deprivation experiments on.
ليقوموا بعمل تجارب حرمان النوم عليهم.
So I would come in and take the test and I fell asleep in each one.
فآتي إليهم وأخضع للاختبار وأنام في كل اختبار.
And that was because, again, this eventually becomes hard on your body.
وهذا عائد إلى، مجددّاً، أنه تدريجيّاً يصبح صعباً على جسدك.
Even though it was a blast.
بالرغم من أنه كان مذهلاً.
It was a huge bonding experience with the other members on the team,
كانت تجربةً عظيمةً للترابط مع أعضاء الفريق الآخرين،
but it is difficult to sustain.
لكن الإستمرار عليها صعب.
So these rover missions are our first steps out into the solar system.
مهمات المركبات المتجوّلة هذه هي خطواتنا الأولى للنظام الشمسي.
We are learning how to live on more than one planet.
نحن في خوض تعلّم كيفية العيش على أكثر من كوكب.
We are changing our perspective to become multi-planetary.
نحن نغيّر منظورنا لنصبح متعددي الكواكب.
So the next time you see a Star Wars movie,
ففي المرة القادمة التي ترى فيها فيلم (حرب النجوم)،
and there are people going from the Dagobah system to Tatooine,
وهناك أشخاص ذاهبون من نظام (داجوبا) إلى (تاتوين)،
think about what it really means to have people spread out so far.
فكّر في ماذا يعني فعليّاً أن يكون لديك أشخاص منتشرين بهذا البعد.
What it means in terms of the distances between them,
ماذا يعني فيما يتعلق بالمسافات بينهم،
how they will start to feel separate from each other
كيف سيشعرون بالبعد عن بعضهم الآخر
and just the logistics of the time.
وفقط لوجستيات الوقت.
We have not sent people to Mars yet, but we hope to.
لم نرسل أناساً للمريخ بعد، ولكنّنا نأمل في ذلك.
And between companies like SpaceX and NASA
وبين شركات مثل سبيس اكس وناسا
and all of the international space agencies of the world,
وكلّ وكالات الفضاء العالمية،
we hope to do that in the next few decades.
نأمل أن نفعل ذلك خلال العقود القليلة القادمة.
So soon we will have people on Mars, and we truly will be multi-planetary.
قريباً جدّاً سيكون لدينا أناسٌ على المريخ، وسنكون حقّاً متعددي الكواكب.
And the young boy or the young girl
والفتى الصغير أو الفتاة الصغيرة
who will be going to Mars could be in this audience or listening today.
التي ستذهب للمريخ قد تكون وسط هذا الحضور أو تستمع لنا اليوم.
I have wanted to work at JPL on these missions since I was 14 years old
أردت العمل في (جاي بي ال) على هذه المهمات منذ أن كنت في الرابعة عشر من عمري
and I am privileged to be a part of it.
وأنا أتشرّف بكوني جزءاً منه.
And this is a remarkable time in the space program,
وهذا زمن حافل في برنامج الفضاء،
and we are all in this journey together.
وجميعنا في هذه الرحلة سويّاً.
So the next time you think you don't have enough time in your day,
في المرة القادمة التي تعتقد أنك لا تمتلك وقتاً كافياً في يومك،
just remember, it's all a matter of your Earthly perspective.
فقط تذكّر، الأمر كله يتعلق بمنظورك الأرضي.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)